I'm going to discuss the loop in 2 parts.
The first part to the loop is the initiation of it.
The initiation of the loop is entering your boat into the hole, trying to pop your boat up into the air as much as possible.
The placement of your initiation is really important.
I want to initiate my bow right here.
Right there is the seam between the green water and the foam.
If I can get my bow there, it's going to get a nice pop up into the air.
I don't want to initiate farther upstream into that area.
If I hit the green water more, I'm more likely to get rejected back.
Once my bow goes into the seam, I'm going to throw my weight forward hard in order to push the boat into the water deeply.
Once my boat gets in the water deeply, I'm going to lean back, reach up to the sky, and try and get as much lift as I can.